<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An impartial description of Surinam upon the continent of Guiana in America with a history of several strange beasts, birds, fishes, serpents, insects and customs of that colony, etc. / worthy the perusal of all, from experience of George Warren ...</title>
            <author>Warren, George, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6956</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13506661</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13506661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67689)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 480:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An impartial description of Surinam upon the continent of Guiana in America with a history of several strange beasts, birds, fishes, serpents, insects and customs of that colony, etc. / worthy the perusal of all, from experience of George Warren ...</title>
                  <author>Warren, George, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid for Nathaniel Brooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Suriname --  History --  To 1814.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99824:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An IMPARTIAL DESCRIPTION OF SURINAM UPON <hi>The</hi> CONTINENT <hi>of</hi> GUIANA IN AMERICA.</p>
            <p>With a Hiſtory of ſeveral ſtrange <hi>Beaſts, Birds, Fiſhes, Serpents, Inſects,</hi> and Cuſtoms of that Colony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Worthy the Peruſal of all, from the Experience of <hi>George Warren</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Godbid</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Brooke</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Greſham-Colledge,</hi> in the ſecond yard from <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99824:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99824:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS is a preſent of three years Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not without many hazards to my ſelf: for the delights of Warm Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are mingled with ſharp Sawces, and indeed from the Conſtant breathings through the Pores, more there than in Colder Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, 'tis rationally believed, our Spirits muſt make haſt out of Bodies exhauſt by heat; but I have often ſeen many both Natives, and others at <hi>Suri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> very vigorous in extreme Old Age. In this Continent, the <hi>Indians</hi> will tell you of Mighty Princes upwards, and Golden Cities, how true I know not. But a brave Country it is, and it may be truly ſaid, to a Mind untaint with Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (and that can live according to Nature) no place is more accommodate; whether we regard health, a luxuriant Soyle, or kind Women. I have made it no deſign of mine either to hide the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of the Country, or to extol the happineſs thereof beyond truth: Such as it is, is here expos'd.
<pb facs="tcp:99824:3"/> Some there are, who confidently believe, theſe warm Climates were the Dwellings of the Antient Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heathens: to which opinion, for the pleaſure of the ſame places, I could aſſent, but that the moſt Acute Philoſophers of old, held a groſs Doctrine, that under, or neer the Line, 'twas not habitable, whereof dayly Experience affords a Confutation: and it's great ignorance to think any conſiderable Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements can be made far diſtant from the Sun. What advantage hath Accrewed to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Scepter, How Navigation hath been increaſed by the only Trade of <hi>Tobacco</hi> and <hi>Sugar</hi> in our New Plantations, Who hath not heard? As for my ſelf, I held it more Ingenuous to venture thy Cenſure for appearing in Print, than that you ſhould loſe the delight of theſe Obſervations.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99824:3"/>
            <head>A Full and Impartial <hi>DESCRIPTION</hi> of <hi>SURINAM.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the River</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HICH is in Six, or Five and a half De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Northerly Latitude, barr'd with Sand at the Entrance: but yet, Three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom deep at High-Water; and in Spring Tides more. 'Tis about a League over at the Mouth, of which breadth, or but very little narrower, it holds five Leagues, up to a ſmall Village, call'd the <hi>Fort;</hi> and then, by degrees, in two Leagues farther, decreaſes a Mile, and ſo continues as far as hath been diſcover'd. It hath a Channel on either ſide, to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> but the firſt is reputed beſt, in which, Veſſels of 300 Tons have ſailed neer 20 Leagues up to the Metropolis or chief Town of the Colony, called <hi>Toorarica,</hi> conſiſting of about One hundred Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Houſes, and a Chappel. Before the Town is a very fair Bay or Harbour, large enough to contain an Hundred Sail of Ships. 'Tis on both ſides Woody, unleſs here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99824:4"/> and there a Plantation be open to it; and ſo perfect a <hi>Meander,</hi> that in a matter of fifteen Leagues ſailing, a Ship ſteers all points of the Compaſs. 'Tis well ſtor'd with good Fiſh of innumerable kinds, and others, though not ſo uſeful, yet for their Rarity very obſervable: as the <hi>Sword-Fiſh,</hi> ſo called from a Bone growing at his Snout, reſembling a Sword, or more properly a Rake, of which I have ſeen ſome above an Ell long. There is another, call'd the <hi>Manatee,</hi> who feeds upon Buſhes by the River ſide, gives ſuck like a <hi>Cow,</hi> and eats more like Fleſh than Fiſh: I'le but name a third, which, for the ſtrangeneſs of its Nature, deſerves a more particular Deſcription, 'Tis the <hi>Torpedo</hi> or <hi>Num-Eele,</hi> which, being alive, and touching any other Living Creature, ſtrikes ſuch a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into all the parts, as for a while renders them wholly uſeleſs, and inſenſible, which, is believ'd, has occaſioned the Drowning of ſeveral perſons who have been unhappily ſo taken, as they were Swiming in the River: It produces the like Effect if but touch'd with the end of a long Pole, or one man immediately laying hold of another ſo benumm'd: The Truth of this was experienced, One of them being taken and thrown upon the Bank, where a Dog ſpying it ſtir, catches it in his Mouth, and preſently falls down, which the Maſter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, and going to pull him off becomes motionleſs himſelf; another ſtanding by, and endevouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him, follows the ſame fortune; the <hi>Eele</hi> getting looſe they Return quickly to themſelves.</p>
               <p>Plantations are ſetled Thirty Leagues up the River, higher than which, 'tis not probable, the Limits of that New Colony can extend, by reaſon of Cataracts or Falls
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99824:4"/> of Water, that deſcend from ledges of Rocks, from one ſide of the River to the other, rendring any paſſage by Water (the beſt means of Conveying neceſſaries) altogether impoſſible; nor is it only one, for which, in time, perhaps ſome Remedy might be invented, but they are obſerved to be within five or ſix Leagues one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for ought is known, up to the very head: There was once an occaſion to go up thoſe Falls in Chaſe of ſome <hi>Indians,</hi> who had been down, and kill'd an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Woman, and robb'd the houſe wherein ſhe was: This Expedition was undertaken by a good number of men well provided, who, after they had with moſt grievous labour hall'd their Boats by Land above ſeven or eight of thoſe Falls, were at laſt, compell'd to return without deſired Succeſs, not having ſo much as ſeen an <hi>Indian,</hi> and adventuring as they came back to ſhoot thoſe Precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in their Boats, were ſome of them daſh'd to pieces in the Deſcent, and the reſt hardly eſcaped with their Lives: Theſe Cataracts are in moſt of the Rivers upon the Coaſt, and are the only Let to the more perfect diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of that rich Continent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Climate and Country in General;</head>
               <p>WHICH, from <hi>November</hi> till <hi>July,</hi> is but moderately hot, by reaſon of Clouds interpos'd, and exceſſive Rains cooling the Earth all that time, and the Conſtant North-Eaſt-Brizes, which no leſs Refrigerate the Aire:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99824:5"/> The other five Months, when little Rain falls, and thoſe friendly Clouds are wanting, the heat is ſomething vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, occaſioned no leſs by a Reflection from the earth, which is generally Sandy, than the nearneſs of the Sun it ſelf, and would be hardly tolerable, were it not for the Brizes before-mentioned. Being no further from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial Line, the dayes and nights are alwayes almoſt Equal, not differing above an hour, the Sun Riſing and Setting never ſooner or later, than half an hour before, or half an hour after Six. The conſtant warmneſs of the place makes it far more agreeable to Age, than Youth; The firſt it cheriſhes, and as it were, renews their years, making them ſprightly and gallant, who were here crazy and impotent; the latter have leſs ſpirit, and decay more ſwiftly than in theſe Northern Countries, though <hi>Surinam</hi> be healthful enough to temperate ſound bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. The moſt common Diſeaſes incident to it, are the <hi>Feaver</hi> and <hi>Ague,</hi> the <hi>Yawes,</hi> and the <hi>Dropſie,</hi> call'd there, the <hi>Country Diſeaſe:</hi> With the firſt, the People were not a little Afflicted at their firſt ſetling, I believe, occaſion'd rather by bad Lodging, and worſe Diet, than any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Intemperature of the Climate. The <hi>Yawes</hi> is the ſame with, or but little differing from the <hi>French-Pox,</hi> 'tis too frequently Caught by Coition with <hi>Indian-Women,</hi> to whom 'tis no leſs natural than any other Malady, and which, by the Mediation of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> is become no Stranger to almoſt every part of <hi>Europe;</hi> 'twill breed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there from any Sore, which if not carefully look'd after (ſuch is the Malignity of the Country to things of that nature) Converts into that moſt loathſome and not eaſily cur'd miſchief. The <hi>Dropſie,</hi> or <hi>Country-Diſeaſe,</hi> is, I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99824:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> think, acquired by that unwholſome flaſhy kind of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, which, from the hardneſs of the place, and penury of Maſters, poor Servants are forc'd to make a ſhift with, (for I never obſerved any but ſuch have it) which, lighting upon dull un-active Spirits, drives them into a melancholy Careleſneſs of themſelves, and for want of vigour and livelineſs to expel thoſe moiſt humours, which ſuch tempers in that Country do abundantly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, they periſh, being hardly recoverable unleſs taken at the very beginning of the Diſtemper.</p>
               <p>The Land next the Rivers mouth, is low, woody, and full of <hi>Swanyes:</hi> One, but about thirty Leagues up, high, and mountainous, having plain Fields of a vaſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, here and there beautified with ſmall Groves, like Iſlands in a Green Sea; amongſt whoſe ſtill flouriſhing Trees, 'tis incomparably pleaſant to conſider the delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Handy-works of Nature, expreſs'd in the variety of thoſe pretty Creatures, which, with Ridiculous Antick Geſtures, diſport themſelves upon the Branches. There is a conſtant Spring and Fall, ſome leaves Dropping, and others ſucceeding in their Places: But the Trees are never quite diveſted of their Summer Livery; Some, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Bloſſoms, and the ſeveral degrees of Fruit at once: The Senſe of Smelling may, at any time, enjoy a full delight amongſt the Woods, which diſperſe their Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Odours a good diſtance from the Land, to the no little Pleaſure of the Sea-tired Paſſenger.</p>
               <p>The various productions of Inſects from the heat and moiſture, is admirable in that Country. I have obſerved a white Speck, at firſt, no bigger than a Pins-Head, upon a new-ſprung ſoft Excreſcency from the Root of a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99824:6"/> Great Tree, which, by degrees in two or three dayes, has grown to a kind of <hi>Butter-flye,</hi> with fair painted black and Saffron-Coloured Wings. I have found others not quite perect ſticking upon the Bodies of Trees, as it were incorporated into the Wood it ſelf. There is another, called a <hi>Cammel-Flye,</hi> from its long neck, how Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted I know not, which has its Wings like ſmall Leaves, and, having lived a while, at length lights upon the ground, takes Root, and is transformed into a Plant. This I relate, not from any certain Knowledge of my own, but I was encouraged to inſert it, from the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Honourable <hi>William Byam,</hi> Lord General of <hi>Guiana,</hi> and Governour of <hi>Surinam,</hi> who, I am ſure is too much a Gentleman to be the Author of a Lye. Many more Obſervations of this Nature no doubt I might have made, if the vanity of my years would have ſuffered me to mind it.</p>
               <p>The Government is Monarchical, an Imitation of ours, by a Governour, Council, and Aſſembly; the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are alſo theirs, to which are added ſome by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, no leſs oblieging, proper to the Conveniencies of that Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Proviſions</head>
               <p>WHICH are <hi>Yames, Plantons,</hi> and <hi>Caſſader,</hi> for Bread; The firſt is a Root, bearing a Bine not unlike to a Hop, 'tis Ripe in Eight Months, and being boyl'd or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99824:6"/> roaſted is drie and crumbly; it has no bad taſte, becauſe it has none at all that ever I could find in't: The <hi>Planton</hi> is a Fruit of a Tree, but of Twelve Months growth; 'tis almoſt like a Bean-Cod, but bigger; they hang Forty or Fifty in a Bunch, of which, the Tree bears no more than One at a time, and being gather'd before quite ripe, are alſo either boyl'd or roaſted, and in my opinion not much more excellent than the former. The laſt, which indeed may moſt properly be termed Bread, is alſo a Root, ordinarily almoſt as thick as a Man's Leg, but of various Forms; it bears a ſmall Tree about Eight foot high, and becomes fit to draw in Twelve Months, when, 'tis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted with Sticks of its own laid in the Ground: The Root is taken, ſcrap'd, and then preſs'd from its Juice, which is rank Poyſon, and, after, bak'd upon Stones in Round Cakes, half an Inch thick; when 'tis new made, 'tis pleaſant enough, but by that time 'tis a day old, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks there's little ſavour in't: Of this, the <hi>Indians</hi> make divers kinds of Inebriating Drinks, one whereof, call'd <hi>Perrinoe,</hi> is truly good, and neerly reſembles our ſtrongeſt <hi>March</hi>-Beer, which has been preſerv'd to a Twelve-month ſtaleneſs: But the relation of their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Brewing it, will, I believe, Rebate the edge of any one's deſire here, which, perhaps, might be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſharp enough to taſte it; Firſt, they take <hi>Caſſader</hi>-Bread bak'd for that purpoſe very black, which the oldeſt Women, and ſnotty Noſe Children chaw in their Mouths, and with as much Spittle as they can, throw into a Jar of Water, ſo letting it ſtand a while, then ſtrain the Bread from it, and with ſome Chaw'd Potatoes ſet it a working, which becomes fit to drink in few days. The <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99824:7"/> Planters make their Cool Drink of the Juice of Sugar-Canes, and Water boyl'd together, a moſt pleaſant Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and ſuppos'd wholſom.</p>
               <p>Of Fleſh and Fiſh they receive Conſtant Supplies from <hi>New-England, Virginia,</hi> and other places, though the Woods and Rivers are not unfurniſh'd of ſufficient quantities, but the inceſſant Rains, and over-flowes of water hinder their being taken Conſiderably, ſave in the day time, when no body need Complain of Want that can but take a little pains to Catch it. The Fiſh may juſtly be reputed Comparable to ours, but, a not very Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Palate may eaſily diſcern, how much better the Fleſh of <hi>England</hi> is, than the ſame kinds in thoſe hotter Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that breed there, being obſerv'd to be for the moſt part, flaſhy and inſipid: Hogs only excepted, which are far better and ſweeter than amongſt us.</p>
               <p>At one time of the year alſo are taken <hi>Tortoiſes,</hi> (not thoſe whoſe Shells are ſo highly valu'd here) upon the Sea-Coaſt, weighing two or three hundred pounds a piece. The Females are Accounted beſt, who have commonly a Peck of Eggs at once in their Bellies, each as big as a Hens, but hardly ſo good, which they come out of the Water to lay in the Sand, where they Cover and leave them to be hatch'd by the Sun's heat: The Fleſh of theſe Salted, I think, nothing but an invincible neceſſity can plead for; but freſh, 'tis Cryed up by ſome for a moſt excellent Diſh, though, for my part, I am prone to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve otherwiſe: The Taſte is not un-pleaſant, but it was alwayes moſt offenſive to my Stomach, which is none of the niceſt; and it cannot but yield a very groſs and ſlimy nouriſhment, becauſe of its ſudden aptneſs to Putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99824:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> not being preſervable from Stinking, without Salt, above two hours after 'tis killed. Sheep will by no means thrive there, being a Creature, I ſuppoſe, more appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to Cold and Dry, than Hot and Moiſt Countries. <hi>Beeves</hi> like the place well, eſpecially by the Sea-ſide, but the Stock is not yet grown numerous enough to find over-much Employment for a Butcher. <hi>Hogs</hi> would increaſe infinitely, did not the <hi>Bats</hi> Retard it, by Biting off their Teats.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Birds</head>
               <p>WHICH generally both for Beauty and Goodneſs, may, I believe, Claim Priority from moſt in the World: But the <hi>Philomela's</hi> warbling Throat is wanting to all, in thoſe too ſavage Manſions for ſo ſweet a Gueſt. The Birds there, making no other Harmony, but in hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, one howling, another ſchreiching; a third, as 'twere, groaning and lamenting; all agreeing in their ill-Conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Voyces to Repreſent the diſmal Yellings of a Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Quire: But what is wanting in their Muſick (which Contributes nothing to real uſes) is more than Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſated by their other Excellencies. <hi>Duck, Teal, Widgeon, Plover, Snite, Pheaſant, Partridge,</hi> &amp;c. far bigger, and every whit as good as any here, are there frequent in all places. <hi>Parrots</hi> alſo are more Common than <hi>Jack-Dawes</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> And, upon the Sea-Coaſt, are a kind of Fowl (whoſe Name I don't remember) ſo tall, that at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99824:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> a diſtance, they appear like Companies of men, upon the Sand, and coming neerer, their glittering feather'd Armors (of ſo pure a Scarlet as no Art can equal) almoſt dazzle the greedy Eyes of the Beholders. Exceeding theſe, for Beauty, (though of far different magnitude, being not bigger than ſome <hi>Humble-Bee</hi>) is a Bird in the Woods, which turning ſeveral wayes, preſents as many of the moſt delightful Colours to the Eyes, and ſo lively, as can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be imagined: 'tis call'd a <hi>Humming-Bird,</hi> and like a <hi>Bee,</hi> gathers its nouriſhment from Flowers. There is another kind of Black Bird which hangs its Neſt like a Purſnet, at the ends of Boughs, to ſecure it from the Roguiſh Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies, who would be otherwiſe pulling it to pieces. A great deal might be ſpoken more Commendatory, at leaſt more Curious, upon this Subject, by ſome body, whoſe Obſervations were intended, not, like mine, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as it were, by chance, and without a thought of rendring them more Publique, then by Curſory, and Verbal Repetitions to Familiars. I would have added ſomething of the <hi>Bat,</hi> but it being diſputable whether it belongs to Birds or Beaſts, I refer it to my Deſcription of things hurtful, being a place more proper for it than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the former, with which, <hi>Surinam</hi> is ſo well and variouſly ſtored, that I think no place whatſoever, can, with more Reaſon, brag of its Excellency in this kind, and it is almoſt as eaſie to enumerate the Stars of Heaven as their ſeveral Species. But I'l treſpaſs no further upon the Reader's Patience than to give a ſhort Deſcription of ſuch, as are accounted moſt remarkable, and which my Memory preſents to me on a ſudden: Thoſe are <hi>Deer, Hares, Conyes, Armadillaes, Hogs, Buffalloes, Ant-Bears,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99824:8"/> Tygers,</hi> &amp;c. The Inhabitants of the Trees are <hi>Baboons, Quottoes, Monkeys, Marmazetts, Cuſharees, Sloths,</hi> and many more, I have forgotten. The <hi>Deer</hi> are much like our ordinary ones in <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Hares</hi> more reſemble a <hi>Pig,</hi> than any other Creature that I know, they are Brown, Smooth-haired, Spotted with white, and are far bigger than an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Hare, which, beſide the mouth, they have no part like: They are excellent good meat, much better than any Four-footed Game in <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Conies</hi> are red, not ſo good meat, and leſs than the <hi>Hares,</hi> but not differing in Shape. The <hi>Armadillaes</hi> are of two kinds, great, and little; of the greater, I ſaw one weighed Eighty Pounds. They are ſhort Legg'd, have three Clawes upon their feet, are Headed like a <hi>Hog,</hi> have no Teeth, and but very little Mouths, they are defended all over, ſave the Head and Belly, with an Armour as it were plated, ſcarce penetrable by a Launce, unleſs it happen in a Joint, they Burrow in the ground, and had they not quite ſo ſtrong a Smell of <hi>Musk,</hi> would be no Contemptible meat. Of the <hi>Hogs,</hi> there are three kinds, one lives like an <hi>Otter,</hi> for the moſt part in the water, and is much commended, but it was never my luck to ſee any of that ſort. The other two are call'd the <hi>Pakeera,</hi> and <hi>Pinko;</hi> the firſt, has the Navel growing upon his Back, he is of a grey Colour, and about the bigneſs of an <hi>Engliſh Shote</hi> of ſix Months old, is indifferent good meat. The <hi>Pinko</hi> is neer as big, and every whit as good as ours. The <hi>Buffalloe,</hi> is reported to be as big as a <hi>Bullock</hi> of two years old, and almoſt as good meat, but I cannot give him a particular Deſcription, becauſe it was never my hap to ſee one all the while I continued there, they having
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99824:9"/> been rarely obſerved to come ſo low as where I dwelt in that Country. The <hi>Ant-Bear,</hi> is about the bigneſs of an ordinary <hi>Hog,</hi> of a black and grey Colour, having a Long-Bruſh-Tail like a <hi>Fox,</hi> or <hi>Squirrel,</hi> with which, he ſhelters his whole Body from the Rain, his Head is ſmall, his Snout about a foot long from his Eyes, he has no Teeth, and a Mouth not big enough to thruſt in two fingers, his Tongue is round, and ſmall, which he can put out a foot beyond his Mouth to lick in <hi>Ants,</hi> never feeding upon any thing elſe; he is very ſtrong, eſpecially in his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts, and has ſharp Clawes above an Inch and a half long, with which, he can ſtrike dangerouſly, but his Pace is ſlow, and therefore eaſily avoided; his fleſh is none of the Sweeteſt, but if well ſawc'd with hunger, it will down. Of the <hi>Tygers</hi> there are three kinds, Black, Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Red; The firſt is accounted fierceſt, but he very ſeldome appears amongſt the Dwellings. The Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which I think are miſcall'd, being rather <hi>Leopards,</hi> than <hi>Tygers,</hi> do no little hurt to Plantations, by deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cattle, and Poultry. They are of ſo vaſt a ſtrength, that one of them will make nothing to leap over a five or ſix foot Rail, with a <hi>Hog</hi> in his Mouth. There was once one came into a Plantation, kill'd a <hi>Bull</hi> of two years old, and dragged him above a quarter of a Mile into the Woods. Unleſs they be wounded, or very hungry, they will hardly aſſault a man in the day time. I never heard of above two or three they have killed one way or other, ſince the ſetling of the Colony: one of them (who was a Huntſman and a luſty Fellow) was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard to wiſh he could meet with a <hi>Tyger,</hi> and made it a great Complaint in all his Searches through the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99824:9"/> Woods, it was never his good fortune; at length, one night, lying in his Hamacko, in an open Houſe, a <hi>Tyger</hi> comes, takes him up, and carries him two miles into the Woods, in vain Crying for help, which was heard by an <hi>Engliſh-woman</hi> in a Cloſe Houſe hard by, who had ſo much Courage (more than is uſual in her Sexe) to fire a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet from the Window; but thoſe who have had to do with them know, it is not noiſe only can ſcare a <hi>Tyger</hi> from his Prey: the Man was found next day with his Head and Shoulders eaten off; they are obſerved to be not ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous now as formerly, partly retireing further into the Woods, and a great many having been taken by the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. There is one <hi>John Millar,</hi> who has killed no fewer than a dozen or fourteen, ſingly with his Gun and Launce, from ſome miraculouſly eſcaping with his Life, and having been dangerouſly hurt by others. There are not many of the Red, and thoſe not ſo fierce as either of the former. In the Woods, are a great many Land Tortoiſe, but not ſo big by more than three quarters, as the Sea ones, their Shells are ſo hard, and ſtrong, that a Laden Cart may go over and not cruſh them, in which being otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenceleſs, they ſecure themſelves from any Enemies, but <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Tygers:</hi> The firſt, breaking up their Lodgings with an Axe; the other, with his Teeth: They'l eat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt any thing, and are by the Planters preſerv'd in Pens a great many together, to make uſe of when they pleaſe, being reputed none of the Courſeſt diſhes there. There are alſo <hi>Porcupines</hi> ſhap'd almoſt like our <hi>Engliſh Hedg-hogs,</hi> but larger, and Arm'd all over with Black and White Quills about two handfuls long, and ſharp as Needles, which Nature has taught them too ſhoot from their ſides,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99824:10"/> with admirable Dexterity againſt a Coming Enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monkeys,</hi> and <hi>Baboons,</hi> are ſo familiarly known in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> they need not a particular Deſcription here; though one thing of the <hi>Baboons,</hi> wherein, I think, they differ from all others, I cannot omit inſerting, which is, that at certain hours both of the night and day, they ſend ſo horrid a Roreing from their hollow Throats, that, to thoſe un-wonted to ſuch noiſes, nothing can ſeem at firſt more ſtrange, and terrible, being eaſily to be heard above two miles off. The <hi>Marmazet</hi> is a very pretty Creature of a greeniſh yellow Colour, and, though far leſs than a <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key,</hi> is Commander of all thoſe lofty Dwellers, riding them from Tree to Tree at his pleaſure, they not being able to ſhake him off, and in ſtead of Spurs, to provoke their ſpeed, he bites them by the Ears. The <hi>Quotto</hi> is black, ſomething bigger than a <hi>Monkey,</hi> having a very long tail, with which he ſwings himſelf from Bough to Bough, his Face is Red, with hair hanging a little over his Forehead, and his Aſpect is almoſt like an old <hi>Indian</hi>-Womans, his Cry is ſhrill, and very loud. The <hi>Cuſharee</hi> is black, leſs than a <hi>Marmazet,</hi> and ſhap'd every way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly like a <hi>Lyon.</hi> The <hi>Sloth</hi> is a Creature ſo call'd from the dulneſs of his nature, ſomewhat bigger than a <hi>Baboon,</hi> and of various Colours, he is ſo ſtupid, that neither ſhouts nor blows will make him mend his pace conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, which one may imagine is none of the ſwifteſt, when if not diſturb'd, he'l make it a days Journey in Climbing up a Tree, from whence, he rarely deſcends, till there is nothing left to feed upon, and then, mov'd more by neceſſity than Choice, he very gravely travels down that, and up another, where he ſits Spending thoſe Idle hours,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99824:10"/> which are not many he can ſpare from eating, and ſleep, in whiſtling ſuch tunes as himſelf is too lazy (and, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, no body elſe would think good enough) to Daunce after.</p>
               <p>This is but a taſt of what another (whoſe humours were not ſo volatile as mine) might frame into a Banquet: though I am perſwaded the moſt ſerious obſerver might Continue there, almoſt ſeven years together, and yet be alwayes finding ſome Creature or other he had not met withal before, and not much leſs worthy of his notice, than any I have named.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Fruits</head>
               <p>WHich are <hi>Oranges, Limmons, Limes, Pomcitrons,</hi> both Water, and Musk-<hi>Melons,</hi> with ſome <hi>Grapes;</hi> all which are forc'd, not natural to the Country, though as good, and thrive as well there as in any other place. Thoſe ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally found there, are <hi>Plantons, Bonanoes, Semerrimars, Guavers, Pines,</hi> and abundance of Wilde Traſh, which, perhaps if Tranſplanted, might prove not ſo Contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as they now are. The <hi>Planton</hi> I have already ſpoken of, from which the <hi>Bonano</hi> is little different, but rather the better of the two, though neither of them, in my opinion, very pleaſing. The <hi>Semerrimarre</hi> grows upon a pretty tall Tree, 'tis almoſt like a <hi>Peach,</hi> woolly on the outſide, and is not to be eaten till rotten, when, the taſt is not unlike to that of <hi>Marmalade</hi> of <hi>Quince.</hi> The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99824:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Guaver</hi> is about the bigneſs of a <hi>Medlar,</hi> yellow, and full of Seeds, 'tis truly a moſt delicious fruit, and when quite ripe, taſts very like a <hi>Strawberry:</hi> it grows upon ſmall Trees, commonly in Savanna's, or Paſtures. The <hi>Pine,</hi> or rather the Prince of Fruits, is ordinarily eight or nine inches about, and a foot in length, the outſide is green and chequer'd; and within yellow, juicy, and full of holes, like a Hony-Combe; on the Top it has a fair Coronet of Leaves, as 'twere denoting its Supremacy; nor do I think it a Uſurper, being incomparably the beſt, and moſt beautiful that ever I ſaw or taſted: it grows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſmall Buſh, about four foot high, the Stalk coming from the root like an <hi>Artichoke:</hi> the Crown being cut off and planted, bears again in ten months.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Commodities</head>
               <p>WHich are <hi>Sugar, Speckle-wood, Cotton, Tobacco, Indico, Gums,</hi> and <hi>Dying-woods:</hi> of <hi>Sugar</hi> very conſiderable quantities are made, &amp; accounted generally better by Ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> than that of <hi>Barbadoes. Speckle-wood</hi> is alſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful enough, and has been ſold in <hi>England</hi> equal to the price of <hi>Sugar,</hi> but by its too great and frequent Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, 'tis now become of leſs value. <hi>Cotton</hi> does not thrive ſo well there as in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and other Iſlands, by reaſon as 'tis ſuppoſed, of the exceſſive Rains, and too far diſtance from the Sea, from whence ariſes a brackiſh Dew, that keeps off <hi>Caterpillars,</hi> and other things offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99824:11"/> to the Buſhes. <hi>Tobacco</hi> thrives well, and is reputed much better than that of <hi>Virginia:</hi> for my part, I am no Smoaker, and therefore an incompetent Judge of either: I think there is not yet more made than what ſerves the occaſions of the Colony; the People, Men, Women, and Children, being very much addicted to the Pipe. <hi>Indico</hi> has yet been but little experienced. <hi>Rum</hi> is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit extracted from the Juice of <hi>Sugar-Canes,</hi> commonly, twice as ſtrong as <hi>Brandy,</hi> call'd <hi>Kill-Divel</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> whither 'tis ſold, at the rate of Twelve pounds of <hi>Sugar per Gallon. Molaſſes</hi> relates alſo to <hi>Sugar,</hi> being that which drops from it, while 'tis Cureing, and is the ſame commonly ſold in <hi>England</hi> for <hi>Treakle.</hi> The Gums yet moſt familiarly known there, are <hi>Montagne,</hi> and <hi>Gumma Semnia,</hi> neither of which our Drugſters are unacquainted with; they are both eaſily procurable, and no doubt many more excellent, which time and experience will bring to light. There's alſo <hi>Caſſia Fiſtula</hi> in abundance, and a kind of Balſam diſtilling from a Tree, accounted ſecond to none for a Green Hurt. Nor are <hi>Dying-Woods</hi> wanting, but more minded by the <hi>Dutch</hi> than <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Plantations,</head>
               <p>WHich are in all about five hundred, whereof Forty or Fifty have <hi>ſugar-works,</hi> yielding no ſmall profit to the Owners, for a ſlight Disburſement, conſidering how brave a Revenue, if prudently manag'd, may be rais'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99824:12"/> from it in a few years: far larger (if no Contingency di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the ordinary Courſe of things) than is uſually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd from a greater foundation, and more Continu'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Seaſons for Felling down the Wood are between <hi>April</hi> and <hi>Auguſt,</hi> it being left upon the Ground to drye till about the latter end of <hi>September,</hi> when, 'tis burnt, and the Soil enrich'd with its Aſhes. <hi>Indian</hi>-Corn and Canes are planted upon the Lower-Grounds. <hi>Yames</hi> and other Proviſions upon that which is higher. The Corn grows upon a Stalk like a <hi>Reed,</hi> commonly ſix or ſeven foot high, and two Ears upon a Stalk: The Grain is about the bigneſs of a <hi>Pea,</hi> which becomes ripe in four Months. They have two Crops in a year, and the Increaſe is at leaſt five hundred for one. <hi>Canes</hi> become fit to break in Twelve Months when they are about ſix foot high, and as thick as a Man's Wriſt: They bear a Top like a Flag, which being Cut off, and the Canes ſqueeſed through a Mill, the Juice is boyl'd in Coppers to a competent thickneſs, and then pour'd into Wooden Pots made broad and ſquare at the top, and taper'd to the compaſs of a Sixpence at the Bottome with a Hole thorough, which is ſtopp'd with a little ſtick, till the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar begins to be cold, and ſtiffen'd; when 'tis pull'd out, and by that Paſſage, the <hi>Molaſſes</hi> drains from it; and being Cur'd a while after this manner, is knock'd out into Hogſheads, and ſo ſhipp'd off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99824:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Negroes or Slaves,</head>
               <p>WHO are moſt brought out of <hi>Guiny</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi> to thoſe parts, where they are ſold like <hi>Dogs,</hi> and no better eſteem'd but for their Work ſake, which they perform all the Week with the ſevereſt uſages for the ſlighteſt fault, till <hi>Saturday</hi> after noon, when, they are allowed to dreſs their own Gardens or Plantations, having nothing but what they can produce from thence to live upon; unleſs perhaps once or twice a year, their Maſters vouchſafe them, as a great favour, a little rotten Salt-fiſh: Or if a <hi>Cow</hi> or <hi>Horſe</hi> die of it ſelf, they get Roaſt-meat: Their Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a hard Board, and their black Skins their Covering. Theſe wretched miſeries not ſeldome drive them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate attempts for the Recovery of their Liberty, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring to eſcape, and, if like to be re-taken, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lay violent hands upon themſelves; or if the hope of Pardon bring them again alive into their Maſters pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they'l manifeſt their fortitude, or rather obſtinacy in ſuffering the moſt exquiſite tortures can be inflicted upon them, for a terrour and example to others without ſhrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. They are there a mixture of ſeveral Nations, which are always Claſhing with one another, ſo that no Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy can be hatching, but 'tis preſently detected by ſome party amongſt themſelves diſaffected to the Plot, becauſe their Enemies have a ſhare in't: They are naturally trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and bloody, and practice no Religion there,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99824:13"/> though many of them are Circumcis'd: But they believe the Ancient <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Errour of the Soul's Tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of one body into another, that when they dye, they ſhall return into their own Countries and be Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, ſo live in the World by a Conſtant Revolution; which Conceit makes many of them over-fondly wooe their Deaths, not otherwiſe hoping to be freed from that indeed un-equall'd Slavery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of things there Venomous and Hurtful.</head>
               <p>THE propagating heat (and paucity of Inhabitants in that Country to keep them under) has I ſuppoſe occaſioned its Swarming with ſo many ſeveral kinds of Vermin, as render the Beings of Men in ſome meaſure dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, troubleſome, and unpleaſant: Thoſe moſt familiarly taken notice of, are <hi>Snakes, Crocodiles, Scorpions, Bats, Ants, Musketoes, Toads,</hi> and <hi>Frogs;</hi> of <hi>Snakes,</hi> 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain there has been ſome kill'd neer Thirty foot long, and of a greatneſs proportionable to their length: I know ſome people are ſo fooliſhly incredulous in things of this Nature, that they will believe nothing which cannot be viſibly demonſtrated within the Limits of their own Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholds; therefore, for fear of being thought to uſe the Authority of a Traveller, I dare not repeat how huge a Morſel one of them will ſwallow at a time: But far leſs danger reſides in one of thoſe huge Creatures, then their preſence may ſeem to threaten; for they are not at all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99824:13"/> and eſpecially when full, very un-weildy: Theſe belong properly to the Water, though ſometimes they prey by Land: what ever they take is by Surpriſe, never by plain glideing; nor have I ever heard of any man yet, was ſo much a Fool, to be Cheated out of his Life by ſo evitable a miſchief: But the leſſer kinds which are too too numerous, are a great deal rather to be feared, being many of them ſo poyſonous, as nothing can be more, as was once or twice wofully experienced, not only kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but the Fleſh in leſs than a dayes ſpace, dropping by Peice-meal from the Bones of them who were bitten: Some are all over diverſify'd with Beautiful and Lively Colours, under which Gallantry is generally obſerved to Lye hidden the moſt deadly poyſon. Others are knotty, with Horns in their Tails, and Tusks two Inches long upon the upper Chap. <hi>Crocodiles</hi> there are too, but thoſe neither very numerous nor large, they need not take up the room of a Deſcription here, their Skins being ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to be ſeen in <hi>England,</hi> in almoſt every <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Shop. The <hi>Scorpion</hi> is black, and almoſt like a <hi>Craw-fiſh,</hi> he lurks for the moſt part amongſt dry Wood or Corn, his Sting is in his Tail, with which, who ever is ſtricken, will be vex'd with moſt intolerable torture for ſome hours, but it reaches not the life: The ordinary Remedy to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the fierceneſs of the miſery, is taken from the thing it ſelf being kill'd, and bruis'd upon the place. The <hi>Eats</hi> are found to be not a little noxious both to Men and Beaſts, in the night drawing away their Blood, and ſo eaſily, that the loſs is not perceivable, 'till it be paſt prevention, which (if I was not miſinform'd) has forc'd ſeveral peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to forſake their Dwellings, to ſave that little blood
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99824:14"/> they had, which would have been otherwiſe ſuck'd out. Some ſeem as big as <hi>Pigeons</hi> in their flight, and, as I have already mentioned, are the only Impediments to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hogs more numerous increaſe in that Country. The <hi>Ants,</hi> though but little Creatures, yet they are ſo many and hurtful, that than them, <hi>Surinam</hi> has ſcarce a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter trouble; very Sandy grounds have always the largeſt ſhare of their annoyance, which poor men, who have happen'd upon ſuch Soils, and have had no more Servants than themſelves, have found ſo conſtant and inſuperable, that in ſpight of all their endevours to deſtroy them, they have been compelled to deſert their Plantations, which otherwiſe they would have ruin'd, and ſettle in ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter place. The <hi>Muskeeta</hi> is a kind of <hi>Gnat,</hi> in the night ſo reſtleſly vexatious, by Biting &amp; Raiſing little Swelings in the fleſh in all the lower places of the Country, but chiefly by the Sea-ſide, where 'tis moſt over-flown Mariſh Lands, that Fiſher-men for Reſt-ſake, have been fain to Cover themſelves all over, ſave the Mouth and Eyes in the Sand. <hi>Toads</hi> and <hi>Frogs,</hi> the Scare-Crows of Women, like thoſe amongſt the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> are frequent in all places, as well of the Houſes, as in the Fields; and in an Evening after a Shower of Rain, their Noiſes are ſo loud, that a man can hardly hear himſelf ſpeak, and the Croakings of ſome of them are ſo horrid, that do but imagine the lateſt Grones of a Dying perſon, and you have it. Thus much is the worſt can be juſtly ſpoken of <hi>Surinam,</hi> though its Contrary Bleſſings and advantages are of far greater weight; nor are theſe miſchiefs ſo Conſiderable, but that Experience has taught infallible and abſolute Remedies for ſome, and ſafe evaſions may eaſily be found for others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99824:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Indians</head>
               <p>WHO are a People Cowardly and Treacherous, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties inſeparable: there are ſeveral Nations which Trade and familiarly Converſe with the People of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, but thoſe they live amongſt are the <hi>Charibes,</hi> or <hi>Caniballs,</hi> who are more numerous than any of the reſt, and are ſetled upon all the Iſlands, &amp; in moſt of the Rivers, from the famous one of <hi>Amazones,</hi> to that of <hi>Oronoque:</hi> They go wholly naked, ſave a Flap for Modeſty, which the Women, after having had a Child or two, throw off. Their Skins are of an Orange Tawny Colour, and their Hair black, without Curles: A happy people as to this World, if they were ſenſible of their own hap: Nature with little toyl providing all things which may ſerve her own neceſſities. The Women are generally laſcivious, and ſome ſo truly handſom, as to Features and Proportion, that if the moſt Curious Symetrian had been there, he could not but ſubſcribe to my opinion: and their pretty Baſhfulneſs (eſpecially while Virgins) in the preſence of a Stranger, adds ſuch a Charming grace to their perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (too nakedly expos'd to every wanton Eye) that who ever lives amongſt them had need be owner of no leſs than <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Continency, not at leaſt to Covet their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces: They have been yet ſo unfortunately ignorant, not to enrich their amorous Careſſes with that innocent and warm delight of Kiſſing, but Converſing ſo frequently
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99824:15"/> with Chriſtians, and being naturally docile and ingenious, we have Reaſon to believe, they will in time be taught it. Their Houſes for the night, are low thatch'd Cottages, with the Eves cloſe to the ground; for the day, they have higher, and open on every ſide, to defend them from the violence of the Sun's Raies, yet letting in the grateful Coolneſs of the Air. Their Houſhold Utenſils are curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly painted Earthen Pots and Platters, and their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is the Leaves of Trees. Their Beds or Hamackoes (which are alſo uſed amongſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) are made of <hi>Cotton,</hi> ſquare like a Blanket, and ſo ordered with ſtrings at each end, that being tyed a Convenient diſtance from one another, it opens the full breadth. For Bread and Drink, they plant Gardens of <hi>Caſſader,</hi> and the Woods and Rivers are their conſtant Suppeditories of Fleſh and Fiſh. For ornament they Colour themſelves all over into neat works, with a red Paint called <hi>Anotta,</hi> which grows in Cods upon ſmall Trees, and the Juice of certain Weeds; they bore holes alſo through their Noſes, Lips, and Ears, whereat they hang glaſs Pendants, Peices of Braſs, or any ſuch like Bawbles their Service can procure from the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> they Load their Legs, Necks, and Arms too, with Beads, Shels of Fiſhes, &amp; almoſt any trumpery they can get; they have no Law nor Government but Oeconomical, living like the Patriarchs of old, the whole Kindred in a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where the eldeſt Son always ſucceeds his Father as the greateſt; yet they have ſome more than ordinary perſons, who are their Captains, and lead them out to Wars, whoſe Courage they firſt prove, by ſharply Whipping them with Rods, which if they endure bravely without Crying, or any conſiderable motion, they are acknowledg'd gallant fellows
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99824:15"/> and honour'd by the leſs hardy. Theſe Chiefs or Heads of Families, have commonly three or four Wives a piece, others but one, who may indeed more properly be term d their Vaſſals than Companions, being no leſs ſubjected to their Husbands than the meaneſt Servants amongſt us are to their Maſters, the Men rarely oppreſs their Shoulders with a Burthen, the Women carry all, and are ſo very humble and obſervant in their Houſes, that at Meals, they alwayes wait upon their Husbands, and never eat till they have done; when a Woman is delivered of her firſt Child, ſhe preſently goes about her buſineſs as before, and the Husband fains himſelf diſtemper'd, and is hang'd up to the Ridge of the Houſe in his Homacko, where he continues certain dayes dieted with the Bread and Water of Affliction, then, being taken down, is ſtung with <hi>Ants</hi> (a puniſhment they uſually inflict upon their Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Dogs, or Children, when they are fooliſh, for that's the term they uſually put upon any miſdemeanours) and a luſty drinking Bout is made at the Concluſion of the Ceremony. Their Language ſounds well in the expreſſion, but is not very eaſie to be learn'd, becauſe many ſingle Words admit of divers Senſes, to be diſtinguiſh'd only by the tone or alteration of the voice. When any Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Expedition is reſolv'd upon, the General, or chief Captain, ſummons the Towns and Families to Aſſemble by a Stick with ſo many Notches in't, as he intends days before he ſets out, which when they have received, they cut out every day one, till all are gone, and by that only they know the expiration of the time, for their Numbers exceed not twenty, which they want Names for too, but expreſs them by their Fingers and Toes, which they will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99824:16"/> ſometimes double, and treble, but their Arithmetick is quickly at a loſs, and then they Cry out <hi>Ounſa awara</hi> that is, like the Hair of ones Head, innumerable. They go to Sea in <hi>Canoa's</hi> or Boats bravely painted, made of one entire piece, being Trees cut hollow like a Trough, and ſome ſo large, that they'l carry five or ſix Tons of Goods at once. Their Arms are Bowes, with poyſoned Arrowes, and ſhort Clubs of Speckle-wood, ſome, for Defence, carry Shields made of light wood, handſomly painted and engraved. They obſerve no Order in their Fighting, nor, unleſs upon very great advantages, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize any thing but by night. The men they take Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, they put to Death with the moſt barbarous Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties a Coward can invent for an Enemy in his power. VVomen and Children they preſerve for Slaves, and ſell them for Trifles to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> They did once Cut off ſome <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Surinam,</hi> and made ſeveral Attempts upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at their firſt Setling, which were always fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, and they ſoundly ſmarted for their folly: now the Colony is grown potent they dare not but be humble. They are highly ſenſible of an Injury amongſt themſelves, and will, if poſſible have Revenge at one time or other, which they alwayes effect by treachery, and dare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Aſſault a Man to his Face. They have no Religion amongſt them that ever I could perceive, though they'l talk of a Captain of the Skies, but neither worſhip him nor any other. They have ſome knowledge of the Divel, whom they call <hi>Yarakin,</hi> and their Impoſtors, or, as they call them <hi>Peeies,</hi> make them believe they frequently Converſe with him, whether they do ſo really or no, I know not, however, it ſerves to ſcare the reſt, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99824:16"/> makes think, Death, or any Misfortune proceeds imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from him. They have alſo a glimpſe of an after Life, in which ſhall be Rewards and Puniſhments for the good and bad, but are wiſer than to pretend to any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge of what, or where. The belief of the <hi>Peeies</hi> familiarity with the Divel, and skill in Herbs, to which alſo they pretend, cauſes them to be employ'd by others as Phyſicians, though they need not be over fond of the Profeſſion, for one of them being ſent for to a Sick Perſon, and, that, notwithſtanding his Charms and Fooleries the Patient dye, the ſurviving friends, if he be not the more wary, will give the poor Doctor Death alſo for his Fee. They burn the Dead Body, and with it, all the Goods he was Maſter of in the World, which are combuſtible, and what is not, (as Iron-work) they'l deſtroy by ſome other means, that no neceſſaries may be wanting in the other life: and, if he had any Slaves they are kill'd alſo, to attend him there. They ſolemniſe the Funeral with a drunken Feaſt and confuſed Dancing (in which they are frequent and exceſſive) while ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of neereſt kin to the deceaſed, ſits by, and in a doleful howling tune, lamentably deplores the loſs of her Relation.</p>
               <p>Haſt, and an unfaithful Memory, made me omit an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, in my opinion, very remarkable, and for which, I want a greater reaſon than my own, to give me ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. I have ſaid the Warmth and Moiſture cauſes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Verdancy and Flouriſhing of Plants in <hi>Surinam,</hi> holding true not only in all Trees natural to that Country, but alſo in Tranſplanted Vines which bear there twice a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99824:17"/> year; yet this Exception I obſerved in an <hi>European</hi> Apple-Tree, which, notwithſtanding the equality of Seaſons, always ſhed its Leaves, and continu'd bare after the uſual manner in its Native Soil all our Winter Months, and grew green again in Spring: But how it comes to paſs, that the Heat and Moiſture of that Climate ſhould not Cauſe in that Tree an Aſſimilation with the reſt (aſwel thoſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted as natural to that Country, ſince they ſay the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Nature is univerſally diffuſive) I leave the <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> to diſpute.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books ſold by <hi>Nath. Brooke</hi> Stationer and Book-ſeller in <hi>Greſham-Colledge,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in the ſecond yard from <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet</hi> going into the <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FAX nova Linguae Latinae.</hi> A new Torch to the Latine Tongue, much enlarged for the uſe of all Gentlemen and Scholars whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in order to their ready Writing and Speaking Latine purely and elegantly by <hi>Paul Jaz Bereny Hungaria Tranſylvania</hi> Teacher of a Grammar-School in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A new <hi>Nomenclatura</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> for the benefit and help of young Latine Scholars; by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Survey of the Turkiſh Empire, Hiſtory, and Government:</hi> Being an Exact Diſcovery of what is worthy of Knowledge or any way ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to Curioſity in that Mighty Nation.</p>
            <p>A Compendious Chronicle of the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal,</hi> from <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the firſt King, to <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the Sixth now reigning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Deſcription of</hi> England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>or the ſeveral Counties and Shires there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> briefly handled. Some things alſo premiſed to ſet forth the Glory of this Nation. By <hi>Edw. Leigh</hi> M. A. and Author of the Books called <hi>The body of Divinity. Et Critica Sacra.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99824:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
